{
  "reference_number": "9618",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "The government should set the target in law now, with the ability to make the target stronger in response to the Commission’s early\n\n advice. The target should be based on the most up to date climate science, on our international obligations and on principles of\n global equity (New Zealand is a wealthy, high emitting country and should do its fair share)."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "The emissions budgets must cover all gases and all sectors, as NZ’s main greenhouse gases (carbon dioxide, methane and nitrous\n\n oxide) all cause long-lasting damage. The final version of the Zero Carbon Act must be decided in light of the IPCC’s Special 1.5oC\n report due this October."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including reforestation, horticultural planting and improved soil health). International emissions\n units will be volatile in price - and relying on these undermines decisive domestic investment here in NZ."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Sooner if possible. Global emissions must peak by 2020 at the latest - and NZ needs to lead."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Three 5-year emissions budgets covering the next 15 years, with our “legislated net zero emissions by 2040 target”, gives the\n certainty needed for action and investment now."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "The last budget should be able to be reduced if needed to respond to emerging international evidence. The Zero Carbon Act should\n\n also permit any Government to act so NZ can emit less than budgeted."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The second budget should be able to be reduced if needed to respond to emerging international evidence. The Zero Carbon Act\nshould also permit any Government to act so NZ can emit less than budgeted. If there are exceptional circumstances, the\nGovernment can change the Zero Carbon Act, to increase the emissions budget, through the usual Parliamentary process."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The physics of climate change comes first for setting Emissions Budgets - the bottom line is what ends up in our shared global\n\natmosphere and oceans, and making sure ecological tipping points are not breached."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The Zero Carbon Act must require the Government to respond by publishing plans to stay within budget as rapidly as feasible within\n\na set time limit that is certainly less than 12 months."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The most important issues to consider are Te Tiriti o Waitangi obligations and fairness within Aotearoa-NZ. This means health equity is\nessential in planning and monitoring - all regressive policies (including ETS settings) must be effectively offset for vulnerable\n\ncommunities. The substantial co-benefits to health from well-designed reduction and mitigation must be considered. Other\nconsiderations include sustainable economic opportunities and technology relevant to climate change, to grow a fairer, just,\n\nsustainable Aotearoa-NZ."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, but also the Commission must set NZ’s Emissions Budgets – like the Reserve Bank independently sets NZ’s Official Cash Rate.\n\nThe Commission can also advise how NZ stays within these budgets, how NZ can best adapt to climate change, and monitor\nprogress on NZ’s emissions reductions."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "The Commission should advise the Government on ETS policy settings so that New Zealand emits within budget."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, but health expertise amongst Commissioners and staffing is needed too. It is also essential that the Commission is founded on\n\npartnership with tāngata whenua and upholds obligations under Te Tiriti o Waitangi."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Adaptation must be a separate advisory work stream, to avoid overtaking the Commission’s top priority climate mitigation role."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I support the following adaptation provisions (which include the health sector): • a national climate change risk assessment • a\nnational climate adaptation plan • regular review of progress towards implementing the national adaptation plan • an adaptation\n\nreporting plan"
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "A targeted adaptation reporting power could start with voluntary reporting in the first year, and require compulsory reporting in\nsubsequent years."
    }
  ]
}
